If you are watching this,
then you know very well...
that the Observers have invaded.
Previously on Fringe:
You can't go back to Harvard. We can't
get in. It was taken over by Observers.
Well, that's not a problem. Tunnels.
Two-and-one-quarter miles of tunnels that
house the steam pipes that heat Harvard.
I must have ambered it.
My Betamax recorder.
I don't think I wrote anything down.
I think I was making a video.
This plan will restore us
and rid the world of the Observers.
You must recover each tape
and follow the instructions...
to retrieve all the parts of the plan.
You are humanity's only hope.
Slowly.
Suddenly you have all the finesse
of a butcher.
Walter, do you want me to do this or not?
This work requires a surgeon's touch.
I'm more than happy to let you take over.
Fine. Proceed.
But it's on your shoulders.
Not even warped from the heat.
- Not bad for a butcher.
- Walter?
That's more fuel for the van.
- I have tape number one.
- Have you watched it?
No. I've only just liberated it.
Shall we have a look?
I had a prescription, it was medicinal.
Welcome to Tape 3 of my plan...
- What about 1 and 2?
- To defeat the Observers...
Walter, you stored
the tapes out of order.
Shocker.
Videotapes must be retrieved.
This tape will explain one of the most
crucial elements that you will need.
You need to find your way
to Pennsylvania.
Latitude and longitude coordinates...
49 degrees, 20 minutes,
2 seconds north...
79 degrees, 12 minutes
and 32 seconds west.
When you arrive...
- Really?
- See if you can rewind the coordinates.
Forty-one degrees, 20 minutes,
2 seconds north...
79 degrees, 12
minutes, 32 seconds west.
- Are you sure?
- She's sure.
Walter.
Do you recognize the location?
I'm sorry. If I've been there,
it's been wiped from my mind...
along with the other pieces of my plan
to beat the Observers.
Hm.
The entire area is undeveloped.
There's nothing around it for miles.
How are roads
in and out of Pennsylvania?
Think we can get there safely?
We'd need to avoid checkpoints.
Long way, considering we don't know
what we're looking for.
Or if it's still even there.
- Whatever it is.
- Hey, Walter.
You think we might be able
to jog your memory if we just...?
I don't think I should travel.
My feet are swollen from standing
in front of the amber all day.
I'll stay here for a bit and regroup.
What?
Walter, are you all right?
I'm fairly certain I
have a blood clot...
because somebody wouldn't stop
at Scranton to let me stretch my legs.
Walter, we're fugitives. We can't stop
every five minutes to keep you limber.
This is it?
Yes. This is exactly
where we're supposed to be.
So, what were you doing out here
21 years ago?
Is that what we're out here to find?
I'm telling you, it was
a wicked tree dwarf.
And I'm telling you it was a kid.
I saw him. He looked right at me.
You know, I used to imagine this.
Going on a mission with you.
You have no idea how many battles
we won together.
You know, it's a lot to live up to.
No. You're even more than I imagined.
Definitely not dwarves.
Don't touch them.
It could be communicable.
Stop right there.
Dr. Walter Bishop.
The three of you.
You haven't aged a day.
You're supposed to be dead
a long time ago.
We were trapped in amber for 21 years.
My name is Edwin.
You were exposed when you got here.
I'm supposed to
retrieve something here, Edwin.
Something very important.
You seem to know me.
Have we met here before?
No.
At least not in the way that you think.
It's electromagnetic discharge.
What is this place?
- You're looking at history.
- Whose?
Ours. Yours.
Mankind's.
These are data cubes.
Stored on them are accounts
of every major historical event...
from the day of the invasion onward.
- You have files on us.
- Of course. You're relevant.
We gather important information from
around the world and record it.
Hm. You have a healthy lore about you.
My son, River, is something of an expert
on the Fringe Division.
We were a group of refugees
from the cities.
My father started this historical record.
He believed our history, like that
of other conquered races before us...
would be rewritten by our oppressors.
Someone has to survive
to tell mankind's story.
What happened to all of you? Your skin.
You said we've already been exposed.
We noticed it after we settled.
Small patches at first.
And then, over time, it spread.
Something to do with this area.
We thought it was the drinking water...
- or the soil.
- Why didn't you evacuate?
What we do here is important.
Even after we became afflicted,
we couldn't leave. It's all here.
Everything. We can't move it.
We can't travel the way we look.
We don't wanna draw attention.
We just wanna be left alone
to record history.
No one wants to come here...
which is perfect for us.
You're the first in a very long time.
But you and your team should leave.
Unless you wanna look like us.
We can't.
There was a plan to defeat the invaders.
I mean, there is a plan
to defeat the invaders.
And I believe it will be successful.
But I don't remember it.
But I know that I am
supposed to get something from here.
I've been here before. I must have.
Search Bishop, Walter.
If you've ever set foot in this camp
before, it would be documented.
Hi.
What's your name?
River.
Wow, where did these come from?
I made them.
Can you sign them?
- These are really good.
- Yeah.
You fought them when they came.
You didn't hide, like we did.
You're heroes.
I have a lot of different editions...
from stories I've heard.
A lot of them I even made up.
I wish I was around during your time.
When there were real heroes.
Well, kiddo, you're my hero
for giving me a nice, strong jawline.
Minutes and 32 seconds west.
Now, when you arrive
at the designated place...
you will need to locate a...
you arrive at the designated place,
You will need to locate a...
To locate a mine.
Locate a mine.
- Hello?
- Olivia, I need to speak to Walter.
Sure.
Walter.
- It's Astrid.
- Yes. What is it?
- Did you find anything in the archive?
- Nothing.
There is absolutely no record
of me being here whatsoever.
Okay. Well, I found something.
Walter, is there a mine where you are?
Mime. The only mime that I know of
is Marcel Marceau.
- What's he got to do with any of this?
- No, a mine.
You said "mine," M-I-N-E, on the tape.
Whatever you're supposed to find,
it's in a mine.
- Do you have a mine, M-I-N-E, here?
- Yes.
It was a gold mine.
These men have something to report.
Where?
Rural Pennsylvania.
In 1923, a mine collapsed in Peru.
The trapped survivors were forced
to nourish themselves on the dead.
Thanks for that, Walter.
But I'm sure that
won't be the case here.
Finding gold in an abandoned
gold mine is not gonna be easy.
I don't know that it's gold.
Whatever it is, it's in here.
I'll climb down.
That secure?
There's something on the other end.
Can you give me a hand?
Yep.
People have been coming
in and out of this mine for 21 years.
Doubt it's just gonna be waiting for us.
Nothing is that easy.
Oh, oh, oh. Snagged on something.
Looks like he was trying
to climb back up.
Same bark-like growths
as on the people here.
- But worse.
- I assumed what afflicted these people...
was some sort of fungus,
but I was wrong.
These tissues show signs of calcification.
Perhaps whatever was causing
the condition of the people in the camp...
is emanating from this mine.
The closer one gets to the source,
the more intense the reaction is.
No one can survive down there.
Until I've conducted an analysis...
we have to turn back.
- This is Anil.
- I have something for you.
Something important.
Etta and her team have been located.
Thank you.
Is anybody else starving?
Here.
- What's that?
- It's an apple.
No, thank you.
Yum-yum.
Do you remember that amazing apple pie
we had just after the invasion?
We were in Boston...
someone had told us
about the shelter for lost children.
We were looking for a place to eat
and we found that dingy little restaurant.
The cook was a mad genius.
What was that guy's name?
I don't know.
You don't remember?
Yep.
Well, that's a first.
I don't remember. It was the name
of the restaurant. Started with a D.
It was like, Dante's or Dominic's
or something like that.
- You really don't remember?
- No, I really don't remember.
The air sample is ready.
Hm.
I think I know what happened here.
This man died of asphyxiation.
Every pore on his body
is completely sealed.
His body was trying to protect itself
against the airborne corrosive.
Somehow,
its pH has been radically altered.
Apparently it gets much worse
the deeper one goes into the mine.
- What we're looking for cause this?
- Quite unlikely. If I had to theorize...
it's high levels of
CO2 and other gases...
introduced to the atmosphere
by the Observers.
From those machines in Central Park.
How would that affect Edwin
and his people?
Well, they're far enough away
from the source...
receiving only incremental doses.
However, prolonged exposure
has created a drastic immune response.
Well, imagine an extreme form
of psoriasis.
Not as extreme as our unfortunate miner
friend here.
Dr. Bishop. I've found an entry
I think you'll wanna see.
Five weeks after the invasion...
a man came,
went down into the mine...
and gathered several rocks,
it says with a reddish hue.
- Was this man called September?
- No.
My father has it recorded as a man,
late 30s, dark hair. His name was Donald.
Says he was waiting for a scientist
from Boston.
- I was thinking perhaps that was you?
- I don't know any Donald.
Well, maybe you just don't remember.
If he was part of the plan you lost,
then it stands to reason...
No, no. I don't understand.
Why would you record this,
a man collecting rocks?
Why is it important?
It was recorded
because of what happened to him.
He was taken away
against his will by two invaders.
So they weren't happy
that he'd taken those rocks.
Why the hell would I want rocks?
Your hand, Walter.
It's on your skin.
Yours too.
We're lucky.
It hasn't rooted into the dermis yet.
But I'm afraid that won't last.
Okay, well, how long
until it isn't removable?
Until it isn't.
Dr. Bishop.
Good, good, good. Excellent, excellent.
Over here. Thank you very much.
I am going to build a suit
that will allow us to go into the mine.
According to the arm...
we'd need skin 300 layers
thicker than a rhino to enter the mine.
So I'm trying to ascertain a metal or
an alloy we can use for the suit's lining.
And in the meantime,
I need you to go back to the van.
- Because I need the weather stripping.
- Sure.
- Hey, Anil?
- I got a call from one of our operatives.
The Loyalists are tracking you.
You've got to move.
Did I upset you?
Earlier. When I was talking about the
restaurant. Seemed like you were upset.
I know you don't forget names.
Donovan's.
That was the name of the restaurant.
It's not that I can't remember.
It's that I can't forget.
Remember when we couldn't find her
that day...
you drew a plan on a napkin?
Yeah, of course I do.
You were talking about
going up to Maine...
to this refugee camp
that you'd heard about.
And I was looking at you and nodding,
in my head I was thinking, "I can't go."
Behind you, you couldn't see it, there
was a wall of Missing Person flyers.
You know, with every day...
the odds of finding our little girl the
way we wanted to were getting worse.
And we didn't talk about it.
I couldn't put it into words then,
but I felt responsible.
Responsible how?
I wanted so much to be a mother...
but I just didn't think
that I was programmed that way.
That I was destined for something else.
Ever since I was a kid,
since the Cortexiphan trials, I just...
I was at odds.
So how could I have
this incredible little girl?
So when we lost her,
I felt like that was my punishment.
My punishment for being too conflicted
to appreciate her when we had her.
And that day at the restaurant...
I knew
that I had to go back to New York...
because I didn't want to...
find...
what I knew we were going to find.
I just...
I just believed so strongly
that she was dead.
And I didn't want to see it.
You thought I went back
because of my strength.
She said that she admired me today.
Olivia.
I saw how you were with our little girl.
I know how much you love her.
And I'm not telling you to forget it,
but the past is the past.
Don't let it get in the way of this.
I don't know why it's happening...
but our family got a second chance.
So I'm gonna take it.
Hey, guys.
We have a problem.
The Observers are tracking us.
Hand me the seal.
Walter, how long
until the suit is finished?
I'm going as fast as I can. Why?
The Observers know
that we're in the area.
They saw us on the highway
when we stopped. Near route 11.
- You need to leave.
- I need one more material, copper.
There's only three roads you could...
Jonathan says there's
an encampment which trades metals.
No. You're not listening.
We have until morning
before they find us.
They'll destroy everything.
All our work will be lost.
You need to go now.
- If we can get down to that camp.
- Forget that camp.
They won't trade
with anyone they don't know.
You know them.
You've talked to them on your radio.
You have contacts in that camp?
I've communicated with them by radio.
But only when it suits them.
They don't even know who I am.
They don't want people going
into their quadrant, that I know.
The way I see it,
you're our only chance.
They don't know us.
Look, I'm armed. I'll go with you.
- We can barter.
- Barter with what? What do you have?
I've got some antibiotics, medicine.
Go back to Boston.
Make the suit there
and come back when it's safe.
Baldies took away this Donald when
he went into that mine to get the rocks.
They read you, find we're looking for the
same thing, they'll seal it permanently.
You don't even know what the rocks
are for. You're putting all of us at risk.
I want to help you.
I do.
But what happens
if I don't come back?
You may be used to facing death
all the time, but I'm not.
These are bad people.
We may never make it back
from their camp.
I have a lot to lose, you know.
I know you do.
The rocks in that mine are important.
And it's true,
we don't know what they do.
But Walter will figure it out.
And when he does, we're one step closer
to defeating the invaders.
I'm not afraid to die.
I just don't know
how to say goodbye to my son.
All right.
What do you need me to do?
Get on your radio.
Tell them we're coming.
Break, break, break.
Kilo-Alpha 42, come in.
Looking to barter. Over.
Kilo-Alpha 42.
Is anyone out there? Over.
This is Kilo-Alpha. What's your business?
I need copper.
We don't have copper.
Let me speak to Ivan.
Tire tread. Matches the make and model
of the van they were in.
Where does this road lead?
Higher into the mountains.
River?
Look at me, son.
What you saw back there in that tent...
There's a lot more to the word "coward"...
and the word "hero" than you think.
It's complicated.
You're not a coward if you're frightened.
That's not what it means.
You're a coward
if you know what needs to be done...
and you don't do it.
I was telling that man out there
that I have a lot to lose.
Our work, the life we have here.
You.
I told him I love you so much,
I wouldn't know how to say goodbye.
When your mother got sick...
I promised her
I'd protect you no matter what.
But I'm conflicted.
There's a time for recording history
and there's a time for making it.
We don't get a lot of
opportunities up here to make it.
I've decided to help them...
to do my part.
I don't wanna lose you.
I don't wanna lose you, either.
But protecting you...
means making sure there's
a world out there that you can thrive in.
I love you so much.
It's okay, Dad.
I understand.
No, you don't.
But you will one day...
when you have children of your own.
The mineral you are looking for
is a crystallized form of quartz...
that contains, in perfect proportion...
will unlock its potential
and create a powerful energy source.
I will explicitly outline
these refining methods in Tape 6.
Or 7.
Without this energy source...
we will not be able to implement
the final phase of our plan.
To my best calculations,
we'll need at least...
18 kilograms of the crystals.
That is about 40 pounds
in imperial measures.
- Did you get all that?
- Yeah. Thanks, Astrid.
Hopefully, the suit will be strong enough
to bring up 40 pounds.
Hey. Contact the camp?
Yes. They found copper
and they're willing to trade.
- How much copper?
- Two kilos.
That's plenty. Too much even.
Okay. Let's go.
I can't.
You're looking for Ivan.
You can give him these for the copper.
They're schematics
for our solar technology.
I'm not coming with you. I'm sorry.
They'll trade for those. They're valuable.
This will get you to the camp.
Good luck.
Don't worry about it.
We'll be back soon.
Wait.
Be careful.
I don't understand.
This is exactly where he told us to go.
- He said he knew where their camp was.
- Well, why would he send us here?
Maybe he never wanted us
to find the camp.
Edwin?
What was that?
It's the mine.
There was no copper.
When he called their camp,
they didn't have copper.
It was the only way to get what you need.
You got what you came for, now leave,
before the invaders find you here.
A hero died today...
sacrificing himself in order to get
the Fringe team...
resources they need to save our world.
Edwin Massey, the recorder of history,
made history.
- Where did you get this vehicle?
- I found it on the side of the road.
The keys were in the ignition.
I didn't steal it.
He will be greatly missed.
Like other great men before him...
he gave his life selflessly
in pursuit of freedom...
and a better future.
Now, this is a ride.